This is the sample document,with the descriptive 
coding visible.  This coding will enable searches 
by date, place, subjects, publication information, 
as well as the full text of the documents.  

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<doc>

<mepHeader>
<prepDate>2002-08-08 KH</prepDate>
<prepDate>2002-08-15 KH</prepDate>
<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
<docDate value="1929-05-01">May 1, 1929</docDate>
<docTitle> <titlePart>The Birth-Control Raid</titlePart> </docTitle>
<idno>msp301329</idno>
<sourceDesc> <bibl><title>The New Republic</title>May 1, 1929, 305-6</bibl>
<bibl><title>MSM</title> C16:0305</bibl> </sourceDesc>
<respStmt> <resp></resp> <name id="SULMA">Mary Sullivan</name> </respStmt>
</mepHeader>

<sourceNote>For earlier drafts see LCM 128:530 and 534.</sourceNote>
<headNote><sourceType>Article</sourceType>
<sourceType>Published</sourceType>
<index level1="birth control" level2="opposition to"/>
<index level1="Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau" level2="raid"/>
</headNote>

<docBody>
<head>The Birth-Control Raid</head>

<p>\"<q who="SULMA">This is my party!</q>" shouted Policewoman <person>Mary Sullivan</person>, in the midst of her personally conducted raid on the <org>Birth Control Clinical Research Bureau</org> in <place reg="New York City, NY">New York City</place>, last week.  Subsequent developments have demonstrated that
this boast was as premature as it was untruthful.  For Policewoman Sullivan's little raiding party, carried out with a vigor that swept
aside as unnecessary such things as common courtesy and ordinary good manners, has proved to be of vital interest to every thinking member
of this community.  And the end is not yet in sight.  As I write these indignant words, the announcement comes that Chief Magistrate <person>William McAdoo</person> now admits that the police, in seizing the case
histories of our patients, had exceeded the scope of the search warrant he had issued authorizing this raid--an act on their part
which constitutes a misdemeanor.  </p> 

<p>After you have spent some fifteen years, slowly and with infinite pains and patience working for the right to test the value of
contraceptive practice in a scientific and hygienic--and lawful--manner, without interfering with the habits or the morals of
those who disagree with you, it is indeed difficult to submit with equanimity to such brutal indignities as were gratuitously thrust upon
us at the clinic a week ago.  Compensations there have been, of course--mainly in the enlightened attitude of such dailies as the <org>New York Herald Tribune</org> and others, and the generous offers
of aid from distinguished physicians.  But even these can scarcely counterbalance the evidence of the sinister and secret power of our
enemies.</p> 

<p>As in the breaking up of the birth-control meeting in the Town Hall, in 1921, the raid on the Birth Control Research Bureau gives us a
glimpse of the animus which may direct the action of the police.  In their futile efforts to annihilate a social agency which had already
been given a clean bill of health by the health department of the municipality, by the state board of charities and by the <org>Academy
of Medicine</org>, our hypocritical antagonists have not the courage to fight us squarely, in the open, but adopt the cowardly subterfuge of
utilizing minor and crassly ignorant members of the police force.  Our research bureau has been functioning since 1923, operating within the
law, and cooperating with recognized charitable institutions.</p> 

<p>From whatever point of view it is analyzed, Policewoman Sullivan's \"<q>party</q>" was a deplorable failure.  A failure, first of all,
because it has exposed a complete lack of intelligence in those who conducted it, and a woeful lack of coordination in the police
department itself.  It is not enough for <person>Grover Whalen</person> or District Attorney <person>Banton</person> to disclaim all
foreknowledge of the raid.  Modest as may be the headquarters of the research bureau, it is highly significant and important.  Therefore,
to permit minor members of the police force, or hostile assistants in the office of the District Attorney, to pass judgement upon its fate,
denotes either a lack of coordination of powers, or a bland carelessness in directing them.  Certainly no official of the city
government, cognizant of awakened public opinion concerning the social value of contraception, and aware, moreover, of the searching
criticism to which the police department of New York City is now subjected, would ever have chosen the present moment as one
psychologically suited to inaugurate a brutal raid upon a modest unadvertised clinic which was functioning quietly and successfully in
an obscure side street, minding its own business and hoping that its powerful ecclesiastical neighbors would mind theirs.  At a time when
the criminal elements of the city--racketeers, gangsters, gunman and hijackers--are so active and successful, it would seem to a bystander
that all the intelligence, skill, and brawn of the force should be mobilized and focused upon \"<soCalled>crime control.</soCalled>"</p>

<p>Even the thrill of satisfaction we have had in the offers of distinguished doctors to testify in our behalf, in the letters to the
press, and the courageous outspoken editorials, cannot obliterate the memory of Policewoman Sullivan standing in the clinic and shouting
vigorously and victoriously \"<q>This is my party!</q>"  I would rather forget that here was a woman fighting against other women who
were devoting their lives to succor and to save their fellow women. By trickery and hypocrisy she had obtained her \"<soCalled>evidence</soCalled>," and now she triumphantly commanded the doctors and nurses
into the waiting patrol wagons.</p>

<p>Whatever the outcome of this raiding party, I hereby call upon the citizens of New York to find out for themselves how and where it
originated, and why it was carried out.  I ask them to recall the breaking up by the police of the birth-control meeting in Town Hall,
with the subsequent revelation that this illegal action was instigated by Roman Catholic ecclesiastical authorities.  We are paying, and
paying heavily, for the support of a great police force.  It is our right and duty to insist that it shall function in an efficient,
legal, and socially effective manner.  Policewoman Sullivan's \"<soCalled>party</soCalled>" exposes it as operating in a manner which
suggests the gratification of private prejudices and unreasoning emotion, rather than the even-handed administration of justice and the
law.</p>

<byline><person>Margaret Sanger</person>.</byline>
</docBody>
</doc>  