<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
    <mepHeader>
        <prepDate>2013/11/13 JK encoded</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2014/04/13 EK clean regs</prepDate>
        <prepDate>2015-02-03 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
        <docAuthor>
            <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>
        </docAuthor>
        <docDate value="1931-03-23">23 Mar 1931</docDate>
        <docTitle>
            <titlePart>
                <supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Federal Churches of Christ in America
                    Endorsement</supplied>
            </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <idno>msp321963</idno>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title type="article">Acclaims Report on Birth Control</title>, <title
                    type="journal">Atlanta Constitution</title>, Mar. 24, 1931, p. 1</bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
        <respStmt>
            <resp/>
            <name id="AC">Atlanta Constitution</name>
        </respStmt>
    </mepHeader>
    <headNote resp="MSPP">
        <index level1="Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America"/>
        <index level1="religion" level2="MS on"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="religion and"/>
        <index level1="sex and marriage"/>
        <index level1="birth control" level2="morality of"/>
    </headNote>
    <docBody>
        <head>Margaret Sanger Acclaims Report on Birth Control</head>
        <div type="section">
            <p><dateline><place>NEW YORK</place>. <date value="1931-03-23">March
                    21</date>.--</dateline>
                <q who="AC">>Mrs. Margaret Sanger, mild-mannered, gentle, but forceful leader of the
                    birth control movement, in whose dynamic personality the whole movement is
                    centered--whose name is world known, who has labored for birth control and gone
                    to jail for it, not once but eight times, was deeply moved when the news was
                    brought to her of the report of the committee on marriage and the home of the
                    Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America. This report, through a
                    majority of the committee members comes out directly for birth control as
                    morally right and conducive to the protection of mother and child.</q></p>
            <p><q who="AC">Back in the days of 1914 Mrs. Sanger, impressed by the need for
                    intelligent understanding of birth control went to England and studied with
                    Havelock Ellis, the eminent pioneer in sex education. From England, Mrs. Sanger
                    went to Holland to study the birth control clinics there. And in 1916 Mrs.
                    Sanger returned to America to direct and advocate the promotion of birth control
                    clinics. Obstacles--traditional, religious and legal, loomed on all sides, but
                    steadfastly Mrs. Sanger has adhered to what she knows to be a need.</q></p>
            <p><q who="AC">Looking back today on the outstanding steps of this movement, Mrs. Sanger
                    cited as most significant the first world population conference held in Geneva
                    in 1927, the Lambeth conference of the past year, but the statement issued today
                    through the committee on marriage and the home, is she says,</q> "a document of
                the new age." "Today," <q who="AC">she continued, </q>"is a most significant one in
                the history of the birth control movement. Today for the first time, a large,
                representative group of churchmen and women has gone on record as being aware of the
                tremendous mass of scientific information which we possess, medical, sociological
                and psychological--and has applied it directly to the important question of the sex
                relation between married people." </p>
            <p>"My work during all these years," <q who="AC">Mrs. Sanger continued,</q> "has gone
                steadily forward. Through education, through propaganda, through the establishment
                of clinics, the truths were brought before many men and women. Truths as to the need
                for the spacing of children, the limitation of the number of offspring, the
                safeguarding of the health and oftimes the lives of mother and child. How grateful
                we must then be to this progressive and representative body which in straightforward
                and unequivocal terms--the result of clear thinking--puts its stamp of approval on
                this subject of importance and necessity. Women's clubs, physicians, scientists,
                sociologists, isolated groups of churchmen have in the past added the weight of
                their approval. But this is the largest and perhaps the most significant group that
                has as yet expressed itself in whole-hearted accord with our movement. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="section">
            <head type="sub">Met Issue Fairly</head>
            <p>"To admit that this knowledge of birth control will mean vice and immortality is to
                admit the failure of the church in its influence and education," <q who="AC">Mrs.
                    Sanger went on.</q> "This eminent group, representing as it does, the
                    <org>Protestant church</org> in <place reg="United States">America</place>, has
                recognized and accepted this responsibility of education and influence. They are to
                be congratulated on their recognition of birth control as a moral and a valid idea
                and for their clear and direct presentation of the findings of the committee. The
                statement inspires me with a wholesome respect for a group with influence such as
                that of the <org reg="Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America">Federal
                    Council of Churches</org> for its honesty and straight-forward thinking. They
                have not evaded--they have not hedged--they have met the issue fairly. </p>
            <p>Indeed, this is the largest step in the progress of the birth control movement. But
                the task before us is not over by any means. Encouraged and inspired by the action
                of the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America, we can now regard many
                of the obstacles as cleared away. But our aim is still to put birth control on a
                truly scientific basis, through research and education and the establishment of more
                clinic. There is still a world of work to be done." </p>
        </div>
    </docBody>
</doc>
