<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Speech">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013/12/04 JK encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-08-21 CH clean regs</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1932-10-31 ">31 Oct 1932</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied>Address to the New Jersey Birth Control League</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421053</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl><title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Speaks Here</title>, <title type="journal"
					>Newark Star Eagle</title>, Nov. 01, 1932</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="NSE">Newark Star Eagle</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger spoke to the <org>New Jersey Birth Control League</org> in <place reg="Newark, NJ"
				>Newark</place>. Others appearing included <person reg="Hart, Henrietta">Henrietta
				Hart</person> and <person reg="Stone, Hannah Mayer">Hannah Mayer Stone</person>. No
			draft version of these remarks were found, the text here comes from press coverage.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="in New Jersey"/>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="clinics and leagues" level3="in US"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>
		<person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Sanger</person> Speaks Here</head>
		<head type="sub">Urges <place reg="New Jersey">N.J</place> Clinic to Aid Happiness of
			Families.</head>
		<div type="section">
			<p>
				<q who="NSE">Mrs. Margaret Sanger, leading birth control advocate, urged her hearers
					to demand political candidates to reveal their views on birth control when she
					addressed 200 members of the New Jersey Birth Control League yesterday at a
					housewarming exercises at the new quarters of the Maternal Health Center, 42
					Park place.</q>
			</p>
			<p> “I want you also to ask the heads of your institutions for the incompetent what they
				are doing to help cut down the need for the appalling bill for the maintenance of
				these institutions,” <q who="NSE">Mrs. Sanger pleaded.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">EARLY MARRIAGE</head>
			<p>
				<q who="NSE">Although she said she believes in early marriage, especially in hard
					times, because a young couple can live together more cheaply than apart, Mrs.
					Sanger opposes the early assumption of the responsibility of children. </q>
			</p>
			<p>“There would be fewer divorces among young people,” <q who="NSE">she said,</q> “If
				they could have at least two years to get really acquainted with each other and to
				have fun together before the children came.” </p>
		</div>
		<div type="section">
			<head type="sub">AIDS <place reg="Mexico">MEXICO</place></head>
			<p>
				<q who="NSE">Mrs. Sanger revealed that she had been named consultant to the <org
						reg="Mexico Government">Mexican government</org> in birth control work and
					has been working in <place reg="Washington, DC">Washington</place> for the
					passage of a bill in <org reg="United States Congress">Congress</org> permitting
					dissemination of birth control information by medical authorities.</q>
			</p>
		</div>
	</docBody>
</doc>
