<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published Article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2013/11/20 JK encoded</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2014-06-01 EK clean regs</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-02-12 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1932-10-09 ">9 Oct 1932</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart>
				<supplied resp="MSPP">Statement on Birth Control in Puerto Rico</supplied>
			</titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421049</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Aids Beverley</title>, <title type="journal">New
					York Times</title>, Oct. 9, 1932, p. 9</bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="NYT">New York Times</name>
			<name id="SANMA">Margaret Sanger</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP">
		<p>Sanger sent a telegram sent to President <person reg="Hoover, Hebert">Herbert
				Hoover</person>, protesting the <org>National Catholic Alumni Federation</org>'s
			opposition to the plans of <person reg="Beverley, James R.">James R. Beverley</person>,
			the Governor of <place>Puerto Rico</place>, to provide birth control for the island.</p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="laws and legislation" level3="in Puerto Rico"/>
		<index level1="National Birth Control League"/>
		<index level1="National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control"/>
		<index level1="Catholic Church" level2="birth control and"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>
		<head>MRS. SANGER AIDS BEVERLEY</head>
		<head type="sub">Protests to Hoover on Criticism of Birth Control Proposal.</head>

		<p>
			<q who="NYT"><person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person>, head of the
					<org>National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control</org>, at 17
				West Sixteenth Street, made public yesterday a telegram sent to President Hoover
				protesting against the opposition of the National Catholic Alumni Federation to the
				advocacy by Governor James R. Beverley of Puerto Rico of birth control for the
				natives of the island.</q>
		</p>
		<p>“On behalf of the National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control," I wish to
			emphatically protest against the deliberate misstatements made by the National Catholic
			Alumni Federationas reported in <title type="journal">The New York Times</title>,”<q
				who="NYT"> her telegram said. “</q></p>
		<p>Over 200 national and State organizations in medical, religious, social and educational
			fields have publicly endorsed the principles of birth control and are sponsoring the
			amendment of anti-birth control laws in this country. It is an arrogant interference on
			the part of any religious group to attempt to suppress the economic and social facts and
			to intimidate public officials who dare to present such facts when these are contrary to
			medieval theology.”</p>

	</docBody>
</doc>
