<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE doc SYSTEM "meptei3xMSP.dtd">
<doc type="Published article">
	<mepHeader>
		<prepDate>2014/04/11 Initial tagging</prepDate>
		<prepDate>2015-01-28 CH proof tags and enter</prepDate>
		<docAuthor>Margaret Sanger</docAuthor>
		<docDate value="1929-04-30">30 Apr 1929</docDate>
		<docTitle>
			<titlePart><supplied resp="MSPP">Illinois Birth Control League
				Talk</supplied></titlePart>
		</docTitle>
		<idno>msp421037</idno>
		<sourceDesc>
			<bibl>
				<title type="article">Mrs. Sanger Says Forces Are Gaining</title>, <title
					type="journal">Billings Gazette</title>, May 1, 1929 </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
		<respStmt>
			<resp/>
			<name id="BG">Billings Gazette</name>
		</respStmt>
	</mepHeader>
	<headNote resp="MSPP"><p>Sanger spoke to the <org>Illinois Birth Control League</org>,
				<org>Brush Foundation</org> and the <org>Chicago Women's Club</org> on April 30. The
			speech was not found. </p>
		<index level1="birth control" level2="in Chicago"/>
		<index level1="birth control clinics and leagues"/>
		<index level1="mortality rates" level2="maternal"/>
	</headNote>
	<docBody>

		<head>MRS. SANGER SAYS FORCES ARE GAINING</head>
		<head type="sub">Three-Year Interval Between Children Is Among Recommendations of
			Body</head>
		<div>
			<q who="BG">
				<p> Crime, overpopulation, and disease would be checked by scientific birth control,
					Mrs. <person reg="Sanger, Margaret">Margaret Sanger</person> noted birth control
					advocate, said here Tuesday. </p>
			</q>
			<q who="BG">
				<p> Mrs. Sanger opened her midwestern campaign for amendment of the <name
						reg="United States Penal Code, Section 211">federal laws prohibiting the
						spread of contraceptive information</name> with a speech before the Illinois
					Birth Control league and representatives of the Brush Foundation for the Study
					of Birth Control at <place reg="Cleveland, OH">Cleveland</place>. </p>
			</q>
			<p> “In the five years we have been conducting clinics in <place reg="New York, NY">New
					York</place>,” <q who="BG">she said,</q> “we have cared for 13,000 women and we
				know we have saved 90 percent of them from death.”</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Cites Alleged Good</head>
			<p> “We have reduced maternal and infant mortality by insisting on a three-year interval
				between children, and thus relieved the crowding of homes.” </p>
			<q who="BG">
				<p> Mrs. Sanger denounced the prosecution of Mrs. <person reg="Dennett, Mary Ware"
						>Mary Ware Dennett</person>, grandmother-author of a sex book, who was fined
					$300 by a New York judge. </p>
			</q>
			<p> “All New York is indignant about Mrs. Dennett’s trial,” <q who="BG">she
					declared.</q> “Her pamphlet has been used by religious organizations for 10
				years. <org>The Union Theological Seminary</org>, the <org>Young Woman’s Christian
					Association</org> and the <org>Young Men’s Christian Association</org> have been
				using it as textbook.”</p>
			<q who="BG">
				<p> Mrs. Sanger plans to organize a committee of 1,000 here to work for amendment of
					the federal penal code provisions in regard to birth control. </p>
			</q>
		</div>
		<div>
			<head type="sub">Sees Progress</head>
			<p> “<place reg="Chicago, IL">Chicago</place> has five birth control clinics and will
				eventually be a greater field for our work than New York,” <q who="BG">she
					predicted.</q> “This city, with its large population of mixed nationalities,
				needs scientific birth control.</p>
			<p> “Under the present penal code even a reputable doctor may not legally furnish
				information or advice on this important matter. In 10 years, however, the government
				will be organizing birth control clinics as an essential part of the program of
				material and infant welfare.” </p>
		</div>

	</docBody>
</doc>
